[music]
>> Hello everyone. Welcome to this session
about coding agents in AL. Today we will
see how we can use the APIs provided in
Business Central to code our own agents.
For to get a quick start and jump right
into it, you can get the latest version
of the VS Code extension. And use the
new project command to access our
templates. There you will find the new
template called agent where you will get
both samples of the code that will be
shown and
and almost ready agent that you can
publish to and see directly in the UI.
You will also get a very nice read me
that you can go through to figure out
all the different parts of designing an
agent and
setting up different functionalities
that are offered by Business Central.
>> [snorts]
>> The first step to designing an agent is
defining the agent type.
The agent type you can think of it as a
blueprint for the agent that defines a
lot of things like the default settings
and the identity of your agent.
It consists of the following parts.
First of all, we have a new enum value
that you have to add to the agent
metadata provider enum via an extension.
This will be the main identifier of your
agent.
Then you will need to also set up a new
Copilot capability via another enum
extension which will act as a feature
switch so that users can turn the
feature on and off. And finally, you
will need to provide implementations for
the agent interfaces which defines a lot
of different things that we will see
very soon.
>> [snorts]
>> Here is an example of the metadata
provider.
You can see that
it has a value, it has a name and then
it has an implementation for the
different interfaces that need to be
implemented for an agent to work.
>> [snorts]
>> This is the starting point where you tie
your implementation with your agent.
Here you can also see an extension for
the co-pilot capability. You just need
the unique name and the unique options
so that your users can figure out
what
corresponds to your specific feature.
Jumping onto the interfaces themselves,
they are what basically defines the
default settings and the behavior of
your agent. The first one is the agent
factory interface which defines the
default settings.
These include things like the first time
set up page.
This is what will come up when your
users first try to create an agent.
Then this is also the place where the
co-pilot capability is bound to your
agent and a few other settings like what
is the default profile that your agents
will be using and what are the default
permissions.
Then we have the metadata interface
which defines the runtime behavior of
agents. Some settings that can change
during the lifetime of an agent. These
are things like what summary page is
shown.
You can Here you can also override the
message review page to show something
different. You can change what initials
will appear for your agent and a few
other things.
Finally, we have the task execution
interface which is the interface that
controls
things that happen
when messages are processed like for
example validation for input and output
messages that you can add through AL.
And what suggestions are shown when the
agent will ask your user for assistance
and the user can click on to proceed.
And finally,
settings that are context specific like
what language should be used on a
specific page for example based on the
customer formatting and so on.
>> [snorts]
>> Going into the message validation
itself, some things that you can do with
this API is that you for example
implement relevance checks before
accepting an input message for further
processing so that you can discard for
example
unrelated messages.
You can add warnings on input messages
in case that you want to
point your users attention to the to
them. And finally, you can also modify
output messages to add signatures. For
example, if you want to add an email
signature.
Here you can see an example of the
implementation of this
interface. On the first one, you can see
that there is code to choose based on
the type of the message and either post
process output messages or validate
them. You can see that we can add
suggestions in the user intervention
suggestions. And finally, you can see
that I can
add an if based on the page ID and
change the currency for example that the
our agent is supposed to use.
>> [snorts]
>> Let's jump into another topic which is
very important when designing agents.
Agent types versus instances. So, okay,
you have defined the type for your
agent, but now it's time to
actually make an agent that does
something.
So, in Business Central, agents are
modeled via instances which are also
users in Business Central.
You have a type of an agent, but then
you have multiple instances of this type
which need to be created.
These instances keep their own versions
of the permissions, of the profile, the
user settings, and the instructions.
You can also notice in the previous
interfaces that we showed that there is
an agent user ID as part of the
method
signatures so you can define these
interfaces to behave differently based
on the instance that they're targeting.
But where do I create an agent? So, our
stop to do that is the setup page.
Um
On top of the all sender, you will see
uh icons that allowed you to create uh
agents if you so allow.
Uh
if you click on them, you will get the
setup page uh where you will be able to
create the new agents. And you will be
the one defining the setup page for uh
custom agents.
When an agent is already created, the
setup page will also be used for its
configuration.
>> [snorts]
>> What is the setup page? The setup page
is a
normal page in Business Central except
we have a new type, the configuration
dialog,
which is uh specifically designed for uh
making agent setup pages.
Uh it has a few parts. The first part is
the agent setup part, which is a
standard component that gives you some
basic uh information about the agent
like uh its name, a toggle to turn it on
and off, and a few other things. Then
you add your own functionality in case
you want to add custom settings for your
agent.
>> [snorts]
>> Here you can see an example of the setup
page. On the left, you can see the setup
part, which is the
uh
standard component, and then on the
right, you can see things that were
added extra.
Notice here that uh the left part also
contains
things like uh disclaimers about AI
usage, which are important to add when
you are designing an AI feature.
What do I need to design a setup page
and to make it work?
The first thing is that you will need to
make your own table to track your own
instances. It needs to be a table that
has the user security ID as the primary
key, which is also what is used for
agents.
And then uh it should also hold your
custom settings for your agent. And then
you can use the agent setup code unit to
make instances of the agent and track
them inside this uh
table.
The code for the page is also uh it goes
along those lines. One of the very
important concepts in its design is that
it's supposed to work with a temporary
table. So that means that you should
only save your changes when the user
clicks okay and accepts.
And on the right you can see a little
bit about how it works. You can also
find these things in the template.
The The main part is that the setup part
the standard component gives you access
to a setup buffer
record that you can use to track some of
the basic characteristics of an agent
like it's ID if it's active and so on.
And you set this to make changes.
And then you also make changes to your
own table when the user clicks okay.
The agent setup code unit allows you to
basically automatically create an agent
when you save changes on it.
Finally you also need to set
instructions on it in order for the
agent to have some instructions.
Another alternative for creating agents
is to create them programmatically. So
you can also tie agent creation to
for example clicking an action or some
workflow. This need to be in a user
session but otherwise it is possible to
create agents
dynamically and you would do that
through the agent code unit.
Another thing that is offered is quite a
lot of functions on the agent code unit
that can be used to manage your agent.
You can set its display name its profile
and a bunch of other settings through
the agent code unit. This is the main
place to look at if you are making
changes dynamically to the configuration
of your agent.
>> [snorts]
>> Instructions are also very important.
They can be loaded at any time during
the lifetime of the agent but for most
agents the most common pattern is to
load them during the creation of the
agent and you can get them from a
resource
so that you can have a nice place to
store them and display them.
Another feature that is supported is uh
KPI pages for your agents. When a user
hovers over your
uh agent's avatar, they will be able to
see uh important metrics about the
agent. So, here you can see an example.
This is very similar to the setup page,
except you can use any card part page,
and you can add there uh
metrics which are important for your
agent.
Now, okay, I've created my agent, I've
created my instances. I need to assign
work to it so that it's useful.
Uh you can do that through the tasks
part of the API,
which uh allows you to automate task
creation for the agent instances.
There is a a set of code units that you
can use.
The most important ones are the agent
task and the builder uh
code units. They allow you to build both
tasks and messages.
Let's talk about tasks versus messages.
For tasks, you can imagine them as units
of work for the agent. They are bound to
a specific agent instance.
They have a title, and they are
triggered when the agent should start
processing. Messages are instead bound
to a task.
You add input messages to a task to give
extra context to the agent except its
instructions. For example, its
instructions might be to process
invoices, and the message might be which
invoice to process.
Uh the agent then creates output
messages to respond to your user.
Multi-turn interactions are also
supported because you can insert
multiple input messages, and the agent
might answer multiple times if it if it
gets a new input message.
Okay, so how do I create my first task?
The task basically requires you to get
your agent instance, uh possibly from
your setup table, and then use the task
builder code unit in order to create the
task.
You create a message for your task
and you populate the task builder, you
call create and then you get the task
for your agent that is waiting for
approval from the user and will execute
when they do that.
Another thing that is supported is the
ability to add attachments to your
messages.
Attachments can be for example PDF
documents that will be analyzed by the
agent and
the text will be extracted.
You do that very similarly through the
message builder code unit. So from the
task builder before you create it, you
can get the message builder and insert
different attachments into it through
the provided method add attachment.
And then when you create the task, these
attachments will be included.
Another thing that is supported is as
mentioned is multi-turn agents where you
can
continue a discussion with an agent. So
when it finishes and sends an output
message, for example, you can
send a new input message to continue the
discussion. This can be to simulate
an email thread or some other continuous
discussion.
>> [snorts]
>> There is the external ID field on
messages and the corresponding method
which allows you to tie
messages to concepts like an email
thread so that you can find them and
continue them.
So how do I trigger your tasks after I
have created the code for it? All you
need to do is to embed it inside the
business central either as part of an
action or as part of a process through
events or in many different ways that
you can try through the through coding
in AL.
Here we have an example where we are
doing this as part of a page extension
and we are adding a new action to the
sales order list.
Again, like with agents, you can also
manage tasks through the agent task code
unit, which allows you to, for example,
stop tasks or restart them,
and a few other things.
There are a few different ways to get
the result of a task. One of them is to
wait for the task via polling,
and you can do that through the agent
task record.
Through the record,
you have the status field, which you can
use to see in what kind of state the
task is in, if it is, for example,
completed or stopped by the system
because something occurred.
And then you can continue and query into
Business Central to get its result. This
is good for unit testing or these kinds
of non-production-ready
scenarios.
The other thing you can do is you can
create events that will only fire if the
session is
is an agent session.
This way you can
have code be triggered after the agent,
for example, does an action in the UI.
The agent session code unit provides you
the is agent session
procedure, which lets you
do exactly this.
You can also use the user ID if you want
to
add events only for specific instances.
The final topic that we will talk about
today is about exposing your agent to
other apps.
>> [snorts]
>> By default, the AL API only supports
interacting with agents defined in your
own app. This is for security reasons,
so that
different agents don't interfere with
each other.
But it is possible to also expose your
agents to other apps by creating an API
for your app. So, what you need to do is
that you need inside your app to create
public functions that
other apps can call. Like, for example,
you can see the deactivate function,
which by default would be blocked,
but because we are exposing it
as um
public method on our code unit my agent
public API, it can be called by other
apps. So, this way you can expose
everything
inside your app to
to be used by external um consumers.
You can find everything that was
discussed today in our documentation
about coding agents in AL.
Thank you very much for your time, and
have fun coding agents in AL.